Kassoy, Bernard Films 6385 F
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Bernard Kassoy Films
1965-1998
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Kassoy, Bernard
6385 F
2 cubic feet
2 linear ft.
Motion picture films.
8507518
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, June 19, 2014
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, October 23, 2015
Biographical / Historical
Bernard (Bernie) Kassoy (1914-2008) graduated from the City College of New York and Cooper Union Art School and worked in a wide range of media as a painter, printmaker, photographer, sculptor and cinematographer. As a young artist, Kassoy began his career in the WPA New York City Federal Art Project in 1936 and was arrested under the name "Michelangelo Buonarotti" at the first sit-down strike against the WPA by the Artists Union. He was also a US delegate to the 1983 International Association of Artists conference in Finland.
In 1939 Kassoy was hired as a New York City high school fine arts teacher where he taught until he retired in 1972. He also taught adult education classes on cinematography at the High School of Music and Art. As a member of the American Federation of Teachers Local 5, he created cartoons for their publication "The New York Teacher News," directed the Teachers Union art gallery, and made stage sets for theatrical productions.
Bernie Kassoy's 136 editorial cartoons preserved by the Kheel Center were largely created in the 1950s at a time when many US policy makers were enthralled by the search for Communist Party members and sympathizers. In pithy cartoons he portrayed the struggles of New York City students and teachers, as well as the Teachers Union's response to these hardships. He accused school, city, and state officials of turning their attention away from funding shortfalls, classroom overcrowding, outdated texts, dilapidated buildings, teacher turnover, increasing teacher workloads, and stagnant wages, to focus on the question of whether any teachers appeared to be advocating Communism. Though Kassoy repeatedly criticized these manifestations of McCarthyism, he was never blacklisted. His work can also be found in the collections of the Museum of Modern Art, The Metropolitan Museum of Art, New York Public Library, and Fennimore House Museum.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
8507518
- Mexico - 1948; Pond (extra) (Box 1, Unspecified 1)
  Scope and Contents
  2 film reels
- Pond, Water Reflections - Close ups of buds & flowers - Paintings to be edited and titled (Box 1, Unspecified 2)
  2 movie reels
- W.C. Film -- Work Print #1; GUNA Sequence - shutter closed -- blank film (Box 1, Unspecified 3)
- Phetrasant (Box 1, Unspecified 4)
- Unlabeled (Box 1, Unspecified 5)
- Silent (Box 1, Unspecified 6)
  Eastman Kodak Company - Cine-Kodak, White Leader Safety
- Original - Guitar Winston (Box 1, Unspecified 7)
- Original - Sculptures (Box 1, Unspecified 8)
- A Lesson in Watercolor -- on tape 2/1998 (Box 1, Unspecified 9)
- Sound (Box 1, Unspecified 10)
  Eastman Kodak Company Cine-Kodak White Leader Safety
- Unlabeled (Box 1, Unspecified 11)
- Unlabeled (Box 1, Unspecified 12)
- AEA '71, 1971 (Box 1, Unspecified 13)
  Kodachrome Movie Film
- Original: Students on Terrace; Model & Still Life in SDY Class (Box 1, Unspecified 14)
- Unlabeled (Box 1, Unspecified 15)
- One reel, several titles, 1981-1983 (Box 2, Unspecified 1)
  Kick -- 12/13/81 & 2/7/82; A Whole Lot of Sunlight -- 3/2/82; If You Go Away -- 3/16/82; Not a Day Goes By -- 4/3/82; The Party is Over - 4/24/83; Just in Time - 5/1/83; All the Things You Are - 5/1/83
- Unlabeled (Box 2, Unspecified 2)
- On tape: P Tomm (Box 2, Unspecified 3)
- Misc. Family -- Bklyn; Bellaire; Lynbrook; Family Picnic (Box 2, Unspecified 4)
- Pietrasanta Dupe (Box 2, Unspecified 5)
- Honey & Baby Merry (Box 2, Unspecified 6)
- GUNA on tape 2/18/1998 (Box 2, Unspecified 7)
- Baby - 1st year; 2nd year (Box 2, Unspecified 8)
- Europe 1965 (Box 2, Unspecified 9)